Today I'm chatting with three of my
AI researcher friends from whom
I learn a lot every time we talk, and
who also work in
fairly open labs and companies, so they
can say things officially.  I am
accompanied by Baron Milliard, who is the chief
technology officer of Zyfra, which
develops open-source models;
John Schulman, who is the
chief scientist at Thinking Machines,
was formerly a co-founder of OpenAI
and led the RLHF work that
led to ChatGPT;  and Charlie O'Neil, who
is the head of model training
at Base 10. The first question I
have is: if it's 2036,
10 years have passed and we don't have billions
of crazy superintelligences
running around and
radically transforming the world.
What is the most likely reason why
that doesn't end up being the case?  Aside from
some kind of exogenous political shock,
or if there's a war, or they ban AI, or
something like that, what's the
most likely technical reason why we don't
think 2036 will be a world of
alien superintelligence?  In other words,
my reasoning would be that it has to be something
similar to what has been a
classic case, almost like Moravec's paradox
, isn't that right?  Well, as
we see, you know, we think that AI is
like, if it could do this, it would be
amazing, right?  As if he could
solve these difficult mathematical problems
, as if he could win at chess
, blah, blah, blah, and then he solves these
things and then it doesn't have that much of an impact.
Obviously, it has some impact, but
not everything.  It's as if, somehow,
that continues and the
true spark of generalization never occurs.
I think that could lead to AI
being extremely good at everything
that people put in a
benchmark, in an environment, but there
still being something persistent from
simulation to reality, which
somehow blocks everything.  I think this
is unlikely.  I think we actually already
see this type of generalization
even in turn-based learning in
practice.  But if it is ridiculously
difficult to generalize meta-learning
, besides not solving
continuous learning, it is simply
super difficult and impossible.  Yes. This
would be my default scenario in
that case.
Yes, I agree.  I would say that
humans have many advantages
over models now, and every time
a new model comes out, it will catch up
in some of these areas.  But,
uh, it's like you end up having
bottlenecks in the places where
the model is weakest and where it has,
uh, worse judgment or, uh, the models can't
self-check well
enough.  Yes, so there is
this cycle that repeats itself over and over again
, where people think, uh
, when a new model comes out and
people are amazed and say, "This
is it, this is general AI," but then they
use it a little bit and after a month or
so it starts to seem silly.
So that cycle could
continue, and it's difficult to predict
how many times it will repeat itself.  And, well, right now you're
not getting
explosive growth in capabilities because you still
have bottlenecks
big enough when you try to do
research and engineering that
, even though the model can write
much more code than a person, it doesn't
make you a hundred times more productive.
But yes, so perhaps there are simply
more of these cycles than
we would have expected.
For me, it's more a question of
to what extent this global optimum of
learner that you could have on a chip
is like the transformer plus
machine learning.  Basically,
like the current recipe.  Yes. So
, I think people imagine that
even once you have an agent
that's better than all humans in
AI research, even if it's
0.1% better than all humans,
the fact that you can run hundreds
of thousands, if not millions, of these in
parallel, and you can run them much
faster (as chips can speed up
), that will overcome any other
bottlenecks, and eventually,
you'll just achieve this takeoff very quickly
with recursive self-improvement.  I could
imagine that if we continue on the
trajectory we're
currently on with that paradigm where
, you know, it's basically like
self-attention machine learning, expanding
machine learning environments, I guess
if you think about what happened with
Moore's Law, right?  As if
we had this very nice straight line
and it would last for a very,
very long time.  But there were many
discontinuities and
discrete innovations that had to occur to
maintain that law of scale.  And the same thing
has happened with LLMs.  For example,
we had this law of
pre-workout scaling and then it was like, you
know, reaching
diminishing returns.  And then we came up with
the RL and solved it.  And then
we got this new curve of
diminishing returns that made it
still look like an upward straight line
.  Therefore, if
another of those discontinuities is required
to solve, I am not sure that
the current method of training
LLMs with these RL environments,
even the RL environments aimed at
RSI, will be able to discover that
discontinuity.  And if not,
we'll probably encounter this
asymptotic curve where...
So, do you think the discontinuity
will be more difficult than anything else
that has emerged since 2012?
If we had the answer to that,
we would have the ability to
implement it.  But perhaps we should
make a distinction between
discontinuity, which
in fact adds to what is our
current paradigm.  Again, it's kind of cumulative.
As if there were something beyond RL
that we have to discover.  Maybe they'll be
able to, you know, connect the
dots on that straight line.  Or, but
again, how far are we from the
global optimum? Do we have to go
back and discard, you know,
gradient descent and
neural networks in general?  And I don't think that if you
keep expanding the current paradigm and
the LM, no matter how many LMs you're
running, they'll necessarily be able to discover
that it's too far
gone.
Yes, the only hope is that
deep learning does not lead us to an
AI that can at least dominate
human research and development,
including the human ability to devise
new paradigms, etc.  Or, I don't know,
maybe humans would never have
discovered the next
learning architecture, but they could have
discovered it at some point.
But it seems that, I don't know.  If we
look at the progress that's been
made since 2012 and we
continue on this path, I know it's been
driven by a huge amount of
computing scaling, etc., but it
would be surprising if it didn't reach the point where it
could overtake humans,
at least in R&D. Especially in the
next few years, there's going to be... Ryan
Greenblatt was on the podcast recently
.  He pointed out that, as you can
imagine, as AIs
become more and more capable and are
able to advance in simulations, it
incentivizes improvement not only in
AI R&D, but in science in
general.  Therefore, this is something that
all laboratories and
many startups are aiming for.  Another idea
that occurs to me is that, if we look
at the Elo rating of
chess robots since the 1980s, there is a
very linear increase in Elo over
time.  But there is a major
discontinuity as they cross the
human range: human experts
always win against AI, and
human experts never win against
AI.  As this
linear increase in Elo occurs, you might
think I agree with your
point that, so far,
AI capabilities haven't been that
important in terms of their
ultimate economic impact on the world, but that's
simply because they are
slowly increasing in Elo
relative to humans.
Yes. Yes, I mean, I
agree that it would be very... I
mean, the only way this won't
happen is if, as you said, we
somehow reach asymptotes, like just
before, basically because, in my
opinion, we're already pretty close to
where we'll start crossing the
human Elo rating threshold.  And then
we'll have to hit asymptotes before that,
and that's the only way that, you
know, in this scenario, I guess,
somehow, we're
sitting here in 2035 and everything is normal for
this to happen, I think.  Yes, I mean
, the only other way is for there to be
drastic regulation of AI.
Yes. It's as if this is the
most likely way this
scenario will actually happen, rather than the
technical issue.
Yes, I think there are different types of
research.  There are research projects
that use a
structured research style, where the
objective is already very
clearly specified and you are optimizing that
objective.  And I think everyone
imagines that if we continue down this path
, such as reducing pre-
training losses and improving
machine learning environments, that will
lead to improvement.  But, as you know
, perhaps what Ryan is talking about is
this much more open kind of science
, which is necessary for
paradigm shifts, in which we cannot
specify the objective and
neither can AI.  We need to
be very, very careful with the
way we specify the
objectives for any of these
things.
And perhaps what you mean is that the
nature of the advances that have
occurred since 2012 is that we have
discovered that in 2012 people weren't
saying... I guess I don't know, you guys
were there, or at least Johnny, you
were there, but I wasn't,
I was in elementary school.  In
fact, I'm curious to know
where the wisdom of the
ages has gone, or the wisdom of having been in the
trenches a long time ago.  But
presumably a major breakthrough was
realizing that predicting the
next token is something you wouldn't have
thought the fast execution of
nanos would be what needed
optimizing back in 2014. But now that we've
reached this new paradigm, you wouldn't
think of doing
fast execution on that and having AI get
really good at it.  But perhaps
there is a subsequent internal
optimization cycle that AI would not anticipate.  And
then there's an external revenue cycle
or something like that which should eventually
become strong, but it's a
very slow external cycle.
Yes, in fact, I remember in the
early days of open AI having a
feeling that just
doing something like minimizing
log loss wouldn't actually lead to
intelligence, because, well, the important thing
is that we account for such a
small fraction of the loss that it would be
overwhelmed by the noise.  So,
just training a language model on
predicting the next token
simply wasn't going to teach you the
interesting things you wanted to learn.  And
we needed to develop better
goals that placed more emphasis on
the important things.  And you can make
all sorts of arguments for this, and
you could say, "Oh, humans
probably don't learn to model
everything in their environment. Most
people can't create a
photorealistic reproduction of some
kind of scene they've seen."  So there must be
, we must need a
better goal.  But then it turned out that it just
worked anyway.
And as you pointed out, the internal loop,
even in current
AI research, such as
post-training benchmarks or
whatever, doesn't necessarily translate into what
users like.
Oh yes, I mean, the whole field is
very dependent on generalization, and it
's very difficult to predict when
you'll get generalization or when
you'll get some kind of
off-distribution generalization.
So we know that if you train on the
task that matters to you, you'll do better.
Yes.
But the most important advances are
usually the kinds of generalizations we
have a right to expect.  For
example, from pre-training
on this
very naive next token prediction goal to
various tasks of interest,
some of which require a
deep understanding of the input or learning
some skill from
pre-training that is very rare and not
very well represented.  And then
also the generalization of these
verifiable tasks to other less
verifiable ones.  This is also a type
of generalization that there is no reason
to expect a priori.
Yes, yes.  That.  Well, this is an
interesting question because one
intuition you might have about
why you would see, ahem, some sort of
singularity very quickly without
even increasing the inputs for
AI progress that aren't just
AI work, is that before every
experiment you run, which is, you
know, a seven-figure experiment,
you spend an equivalent amount of
computation on AI work.  And so
you have automated versions of
yourselves that spend a century thinking about
what the optimal experiment is to
perform, doing
small-scale ablations,
literally developing like a century's worth of theory.
So, going back even before
deep learning.  And before
deciding which experiment to perform,
do something extremely optimal, such as
setting up the experiment.  Then you spend
ages thinking after the
experiment is over, kind of
analyzing what happened and what
the next experiment should be.
Yes.
Well, I think if you think about it
enough, you probably could
have expected some of these things
beforehand.  For example,
there is probably some very
clever way to do a
small-scale experiment that allows you to
build a theory that will then be
generalized to a large-
scale experiment.  Therefore, I would expect that
, for example, we are nowhere near the
limit of how well
research can be done, and I envision a future where
AI is doing a lot of
analysis and building theories,
spending an amount of computing power
comparable to what you spend on the
experiments themselves, doing various
types of analysis and building a
theory around what we have seen so far
.
I think there are very concrete examples of
this when the objective is well
specified.  Therefore, again,
all that thinking can do
is update your posterior based
on, you know, the bits you've gained
since you formed your anterior.  You can't
get new bits just by thinking.  But
when the objective is well
specified and data is available,
I imagine there will be a great
acceleration in the current paradigm we
are in.  A good example of this
is that, if you have an AI that thinks about
the scaling laws of the cat plan,
an AI at this point would have
realized that, well, they've only taken
these intermediate control points and have
n't taken annealing into account.  And
that's incorrect.  And he would have
detected that years earlier.  We would have made
progress, we would have managed to cut
one or two years of progress simply
with that observation made by
an artificial intelligence.  And
again, once the goal
is well specified, which is like
less pre-
training loss or whatever, there are many,
many good examples where, if you
thought about it a little more, you could have
significantly reduced the
things you've done.  So, how does the
new P and how does the learning rate
scale with the model size, and
realize that the model width
is also important in that.  I feel like
you can really backtrack
on a lot of these things and cut a lot of
fruit.  So I imagine a
10x acceleration if our goal
is simply to maximize the objective we're
currently working towards, but I don't see
how that generalizes at all
to, you know, reaching the
right objective in the first place.  So,
just thinking doesn't necessarily buy you
the right goal in the first place.    I
mean, yes, I think this is
really the key question for
any kind of very fast ASI like
the current ASIs: how can
ASIs be generalized to learn their
own objectives?  Because to have
any kind of
self-propelled automated loop, you need the AI ​​to
propose goals, well,
figure them out, propose a new goal, and for
this not to derail at any
point for a long time.  Going back
to the Movic paradox, there could be
a case in the Movic paradox where
we think about this type of autonomy
and in a way encapsulate
ourselves so that we can, you know,
think about what we should do
ourselves and then do it and have
this loop is very easy because we always
do this.  And, obviously,
evolution needs to create creatures that
can survive on their own
for long periods of time.  And
this could be something that, for some
reason, is very difficult for AI, in
the same way that
locomotion is very difficult,
while math is very
easy for us despite being very difficult
for us.    I do
n't know,
doesn't the increased time horizon suggest that's the case?
Yes, exactly.  I mean, this is
another possibility, but I agree there's
no obvious evidence of this;
in fact, the fact that our
agents are now very persistent and it's
crazy to do this is
kind of evidence against it.  But this
could be, you know, one of the
potential reasons why we didn't
get this immediate takeoff, if it
's difficult.    Looking
back from 2012 to
now, or perhaps from when
you started researching until now,
what part of all the innovations
that have occurred since then,
including purely engineering ones,
including purely conceptual ones,
seems like it would be the last thing
humans would have to do
before AI
completely automates AI R&D?
Probably, it's simply a matter of intuitively asking the
right questions.
For example, if you can get
AI to do any experiment, you have
to decide which experiments to do.  And right now
I think AI isn't very
good at this compared to
coding experiments.
Yes.
Whenever we talk about research,
they propose a lot of
miscellaneous things that are very, very
small steps.
Or even move away from DeepMind's approach
that we're going to solve intelligence
by learning to play games at a
superhuman level.  That will be the approach
used by any researcher
like Radford, who will say: "I'm going to
try to predict the next token
from a very wide swath of data
."  And then, even after
Radford figured it out, right?  It took
some time before people
decided to expand it because
the idea of ​​expanding it had to be considered, as well as
the fact that
these things could be predicted very reliably.  Yes.
Yes. I would say that the ultimate job
for humans, or the role for
humans that will last the longest, is to
define the goal and decide what we
really want.  In that same
vein, something like deciding how
the AI ​​or assistant should behave, or
what it really means to be useful, or
what the goal is when we work
with all of this based on
human feedback, is
precisely one of those things I'm
referring to.  And then, later on,
defining the constitutions and
specifications of the model, yes, that's
another thing.  And I think that, even if AI
can do all the technical work, we
will still have to do much more and
decide what we really want.
Yes. Alignment is the final step
.
Yes, alignment is a kind of
answer, but alignment
itself can also be broken down into
a kind of
goal specification, or figuring out what
the right goal should be, and then
actually achieving or optimizing the
goal you've defined.  And I believe
that the first one of them is not going to
disappear in the short term.
Yes.
And if I think about a
post-training team and why you need so
many people on the team, it's
simply because there are so many
different areas where you have to
figure out how the model should behave
.  And the thing is, there's no way to...
there's no way to...it would be very difficult
to automate the whole thing just because
someone has to think about how
the model should behave in this
area.
Jane Street began using Artifice
Assist to test their software in
early 2025. And they were so
impressed with the product that
they decided to invest in the company.  I recently
met with Ron Minsky, who
co-directs the technology group at Jane
Street, to ask him how
Antithesis fits in.
What I think is most impressive
about Antithesis is that we started using it
on a team that was creating
highly secure software and being very
careful, and yet it was still able to
eliminate bugs that would otherwise have been
very difficult to
find.  And that's important because it
helps make those systems more
reliable, but also because it helps
the teams that create them move
faster.
This becomes more relevant as
code production becomes
automated.
I think that, in general, as
we use more agents, the
main problem one encounters is the
bottleneck in verification.    It's
simply the time it takes
people to look at the code and figure out
if it's something you really want to
accept in your production software.
And the tools that improve
testing are incredibly useful in
that regard.  They simply alleviate the
verification bottleneck and
allow you to do more and move
faster because you can have more
confidence that the code generated
by the agent is not introducing
new problems.
To see how Antithesis fits into your
development process, visit
antithesis.com/morecash.
What is the reason why there is no
major consolidation among
model suppliers?  There are many
things that point to centralization
here.  Is there anything?  Yes, if
we analyze the course of the years, is there
really anything that will prevent
that from happening in the end?
Yes, I think distillation is the
main thing that fights the
centralizing force because, basically,
anything that can be learned
through RL can be distilled very
easily because it's a small
amount of bits.  It's something that can be
learned from a small
amount of data.  Therefore, if
model trajectories, i.e., behavior, can be collected, it can be
easily distilled.
Therefore, I believe that distillation is one
of the things that combat
centralization.  There is also the
possibility that there are
company-specific models from which to
learn through
implementation, and that the company can
continuously improve its own model.  And such a
system could be provided by
the current oligopoly of
model suppliers or by some other smaller company
.  But I think that will change
the rules of the game a bit.
Yes, and I also want to point out that
continuous learning doesn't stop the
distillation, right?  Even if the
model keeps improving every day,
you could be
constantly distilling it.  Therefore, it's as
if the loops could operate at the same
rate.
Sure, that makes sense.  Okay, copy
the model's behavior.  I suppose
you need to know what the
correct distribution is in order to request
the relevant model behavior.
Ah yes, to simply distill with
supervised learning, the
distribution of requests is
extremely important.  Therefore
, distilling a model is not trivial
, even if you have full access to
it and have the thought process and
everything.  Yes, it's not trivial to distill all of its
useful capabilities,
because you need to ask the model for
something and you need to ask it with
realistic requests; you need to have
a really wide distribution of
realistic requests.  So, yes,
one thing that has come to light
recently is that some of the
Chinese companies are probably
using these router services that
are designed to allow
people in China to use
US border models that
would otherwise be blocked in China.  But
there are all these
router or proxy services that allow
people in China to use these models
mainly for encoding.  And
these router services collect
and sell some of the data.
Therefore, I believe this is a
very useful dataset for distillation
because it gives you the
perfect indication distribution.
Yes. I think this is one of those things where
AI helps a lot.  For
example, if you look at, for example, the
frontier pipelines or, for example,
the Chinese models that they include in their
articles, there are many humans or
they get initial indications from
somewhere, which is a combination
of humans [] this kind of data, and
then they synthesize a broad coverage
of those initial indications
using their existing models or the
other frontier models.  Therefore
, it's as if you could automate much
of this gathering of
instructions, distribution, and
environment creation.  It's as if
humans need to provide fewer and
fewer bits as the models
improve.
Correct.  Or so it seems, it seems that
you are still limited by having a
service that has users or users
who are passing through it.
So, not necessarily, I mean
, yes, that's obviously very useful
, but in theory you can think about
what users want or do
n't want, but it's like the goal is for
the user not to say, "Make me an
app like this."  Oh, that didn't
work.  Actually, I want you to
create this new feature, but then
relist it and do this other
thing.  And capturing all that trail is, or
to the extent that you could have done it
anyway, then you just
have RSI anyway.
Yes, I mean, ultimately
, if you have this loop fully
automated, that's basically RSI,
right?  It's as if the AI ​​decides, the
data decides the training, that
's the loop.  But yes, I mean, it
depends on how much human information
you need.  As if at some point
you said, "I want traces that look like this
."  You tell the model.  The
model will be able to provide a
fairly good approximation.
If you want to do something like become
a good politician, you have to
anticipate the new, like what
would a debate in the
Senate halls be like or something like that?
Yes, I mean, there are going to be a lot of
things.  Ironically, I think this is
easier for distillers than
for cutting-edge laboratories, don't
you?  Because distillers
simply say, "I want a good
politician."  They are moving to the
cutting-edge model.  The avant-garde model already
knows how to be a good politician.
Therefore, it simply generates these
traces.  Whereas, if
you really want to build the first model that
does this, you have to somehow obtain
data on what
politicians do every day and
build it.  Therefore, it is much
easier to say I want something like
this and then have AI produce a
billion variations than to create
something like this in the first place.
I think a very specific prediction can be made
based on this
observation that
Chinese labs have this router dollar.
Therefore, I think what this
originally did was that I said, "Isn't it
strange how Sonnet 5 and Opus 5 are,
like, almost objectively worse models
than the GLM 5.3 K Mi K3, even though
they have had access not only to
distillation but to the
logical distillation of, say, Methos?"  And
then the counterattack here was
something like: "Well, the
distribution of indications really
matters. It's like you need to see
what users are doing in order to
distill these kinds of behaviors and
things."  I think the prediction here
is that frontier labs don't
necessarily have much of an advantage, if
any, in
RL environments now because, yes,
user distribution matters for
overall behavior, etc., but
the best measure of a capability is the
very, very hard RL environments you
've created at the frontier.  And
then, if you have access to those
RL environments like Anthropic and you have
access to a larger distillation and you
've still created a worse model,
then maybe the
real-world application matters
more than the environment.  That's really
interesting.  But they had to
incentivize those capabilities
first in Fable or in the
frontier model.  And it's strange that they can't
incentivize them again.
Yes. Or
with a smaller model or something like that
.
Perhaps we are in this strange
uncanny valley where, you know,
we try too hard to copy that
frontier model.  As if the gap between
students and teachers or whatever was
too big, and I think maybe
people made this clear with Opus.  It's
as if the difference between Opus 4.5 and
Opus 5 is that Opus 5 really gives the
feeling of having this kind of AI
as a judge that checks every possible
thing it has done.  It's like that's why
they use so many tokens, they try to
think about all these things, but they don't
necessarily have that great
Fable-like model smell to know when to
stop doing that or when it's a good
path to follow or whatever.
The investigation sees the grass.
Yes.
Yes, we would offer a
slightly different hypothesis.  So, I would say there are
a couple of different axes for
the environments you can create.  And one of
them is difficulty and the other is
realism.  It is fairly easy to create, or
comparatively easy to create, many
difficult environments.  Such as those that
involve doing a much more
complicated task or doing something that requires
much more intelligence.  And you could
say that this is like the
reference distribution because many of the
most prominent benchmarks
just involve doing a very
difficult task, like a puzzle, that's easy
to verify.  And then there's something like
the realism axis, where you want
the model to be good in the
realistic coding agent environment,
where there are like multiple back-and-
forths with the human and there are like
multiple goals.  And as I would say,
the people in the labs who
are working out the model's behavior
for the first time need to put
effort in both directions, and to
get good
model behavior you need to put a lot of effort into the
realism axis and have rubrics
or some kind of
human feedback that informs the
reward function you use there.  But I think that
when you try to do a
naive distillation, you end up simply matching
the professor on the benchmarks
in the distribution.  But if you don't have
enough environments that actually
exercise the skills in these
more complex, realistic settings,
then you're not going to get them
incorporated into your student model.  And
I think that perhaps one of the things that
is happening is that large
models generalize better from
limited and complicated tasks to these
more realistic types of tasks.  So
, if you have a
realistic and very good distribution of indications for
distillation, you can match
the large model very well.  But, if
you only have this easily verifiable distribution of tasks
, then
you can match the larger model on
all benchmarks.  But
you fare worse in this
broader distribution.  So that might even
explain something about
smaller anthropic models like Sonnet
5, although it's hard to predict
exactly what they're doing to
train those models afterward.    It
could also be that they are always
changing their post-training stack
, and they simply made
some mistakes in some of these
models.  So, I don't know, they raised it a bit
too high and created some
quirks that people really do
n't like.  Therefore, it is very
easy to ruin
subsequent training in some way that does not
appear in the benchmarks.    I mean
, but just one very
basic point is that, just like
cutting-edge AI labs
buy all the data from
big data companies, the Chinese
can also buy the same data from
data companies.  And they are;  Many
people are annoyed by
this, but if they have the exact
same data and the
means to purchase it,
they can also distill it;  This means that it's
quite easy to keep up
with the whole process.
Yes, yes, yes.  Okay, the other question I
had is: how will
the first models
capable of automating AI R&D actually be trained
?  Because there's a toy version,
which is this thing Ryan was talking about
, which is simply
having GPT-8s to try and build
GPT-3-sized models that are
really good at
internal loop-type challenges to beat video games
that require continuous learning or
just reaching a certain
loss with, for example, the least
amount of computation, etc.  But John,
I think you've said something interesting,
which may not be how it will happen
in practice.  So I'd like to
know how you'll
likely train them when the time comes
that you're able to automate
our R&D.
Yes, I think we'll probably do a
combination of learning from
human feedback to
absorb the researchers' preferences
and creating many practice environments
that involve carrying out
multi-step research projects.  So
I think that, in practice, people
will do a combination of those two
things and, in each iteration, patch
what seems to be most broken in the
last iteration.  Researchers
will use AI a lot, and we'll notice
that it has some
persistent weaknesses, and then those things will be
patched by gathering
human feedback or creating
environments.
Yes, that makes sense.
Perhaps a useful way to think about
this is how much of the lineage we revert
and then let the user play from
there.  I think at the extreme,
as you can imagine, you just give them
a GPU and maybe neural networks or
something and tell them, okay, figure out
how to train a model to do
this particular task.  The way
it currently works is that
we get to the edge of the lineage and
say, "Okay, here are the
bugs that Anthropic has found in
its training stack over the
past few months; we'll turn these into
environments that you need to train in
to improve at the frontier."  So
obviously you block all
previous lineage history, but you could
imagine a world where you go back to
, you know, before GRPO or
something, and then you have environments
trying to figure out what's best for
RL models.  And then, maybe,
you go back further and further, but I think we'll
continue to have so many
computing bottlenecks that people will
continue to stay on the frontier and
basically compare the bugs and
improvements they found since the
last version of the model,
turning them into
training environments.
But it's also very good for having
new, non-steel data between
model generations.  It's simply
... Again, it's basically
continuous learning within the
AI ​​lab that involves
distilling the last 3 months
of AI research progress
through environments and things like RLHF
back into the model itself.
And it's distillation, right?  And perhaps that's why
some of us feel it's
asymptotic, as if you're always
trying to make the last 3 months
of progress.  And that progress is
being contributed to by AI, of
course, but there are still
humans in the loop and it seems that, you
know, you're getting closer and closer
to what
human researchers are discovering and are
capable of doing.
Yes. I mean, all I'll say
is that, obviously, if you're just
distilling into trajectories,
you'll never be able to overcome it, but environments
can go far beyond what
humans can do.  It's very easy to
design an environment that no human
can solve, but AI
can always distill it and try to solve it.
And that would be the way forward, like
the research into human AI.  Do
you have any examples in terms of
RSI or, you know, working on
translation?
But doing it even faster
than a human speedrunner.  Yes. I mean
, I think in
AI research, especially, it's very easy
to define goals, like, you know,
you could say the loss should be
1.3 or something, and no human
can achieve that, you know, right now.
But it's an extremely
measurable and verifiable task in AI; if
AI can do it, then great.
Or I don't know, build a model with 100
million parameters that surpasses
Minecraft.  It might be too easy
, but it beats much more
complicated games or something like that.  Isn't it
crazy to call a model with 100 million
parameters to beat Minecraft
too easy?  Imagine
if I had said that 5 years ago.
I would say that much of
research is not exactly like that,
where it's about climbing a hill
towards a well-defined goal.  It's
more like: "We have an
intuition about how
the models should be improved" and we also have
an idea for an algorithm that seems to
go somewhat in this direction.  So
, let's devise a task that is
designed to show signs of life
in this approach.  And, for example, to see if
we get any signs of life.  And
if we do that, we can make
successively more realistic versions of the
task.
Correct.  He is much more guided by
intuition.  And then, the inner loop
consists of either obtaining the intuition or
testing that intuition
instead of the test itself
leading to the idea.
Correct.  As if you weren't
directly optimizing for the
ultimate goal that matters to you or the
practical production objective.  It's
as if you're relaxing your objective a little
.  You're saying, "Yes, let's
relax a little on the axis of
realism and find some methods
that actually work."  And then,
we'll try to return to realism later on
, when the method has matured a
bit.
Yes.
And then there is also research
that is more focused on explaining
things and developing a theory or
a kind of...yes, we often don't
have mathematical theories in
machine learning that are
predictive;  But we have, let's say, a
large number of more
informal theories about what's going on
.
Yes, I mean, presumably the
models will be trained on a
combination of all these tasks.  And
some will be very easy to
verify.  Some will be like a
trial or will simply ask the
human if this seems reasonable.  And
then you will sit down.  The hope would be
that all of this would become generalized to these
more difficult,
vague, and diffuse types of tasks.  And it probably will
to some extent if it becomes widespread
enough that the cycle
can become self-sealing without
humans being in the cycle at all.    It
's not clear.
Yes, yes, yes.  Well, maybe by taking a
step back.  This is what I think
the plan for
AI research is in the future.  Tell me if you think it will
work or if you
agree with this characterization.
So, the bet is that we'll scale up
RLVR training across millions of
diverse environments in hundreds of
different types of domains, and what
will emerge at the other end is an
agent that has learned these
basic, or
less-than-basic, skills around being
persistent, being able to classify
information and context, and
ultimately having
end-to-end optimization of working with other
agents and things like that.  And this agent
will be very efficient at sampling
within the context.  You know, you've
researched how to really scale
learning in context to be
arbitrarily long, but you keep
scaling it, and so what comes out at the
other end will be something that
basically functions like a great
remote worker over the course of
a week or a month.  Firstly, do
you agree that this is the
laboratories' strategy, and
secondly, is it sufficient?
Basically, learning how to learn
within these simulations, inside
a data center.  And then
implement it in the real world, but not
really learn from the
real-world implementation, just
learn these meta-skills from
simulated environments in the
data center.
Yes, I think it's now difficult to separate
what part of the
labs' effort is going towards
direct RSI versus creating
general smart models that they
can continue to implement to
raise revenue to fund the
next big training series.  Yes,
I think that for the latter, yes, they're
probably only making a little bit of a profit
.  As and and the
pattern of where
these environments have been heading in recent years is very clear.    I
mean, Anthropic's lineage of environments
is a very clear example of
this.  As you know, we first
focus on coding and we're going to be
very good at that.  And then there's the
horizon of tasks we have from
coding, which is probably the
easiest fruit to reach in
terms of data available on the
internet to create environments, like your
own internal material that you can
turn into environments.  Then we will
generalize.  We're going to get into
finance next, and
literally a lot of Excel data and
all that kind of stuff in our
training.  And then, you know, there are
the PowerPoints.  It's like this long
tail of the labor economy, and that
seemed to work very well, and as
many of the other labs and
even open-source labs have
now realized,
that was the right bet.
But what does that imply?  When I invited
Dario to the podcast, I asked him if he
really expected models to be
similar to humans in their ability
to learn on the job. Why
would he try to incorporate all those
skills from working with PowerPoint or
something like that? Wouldn't he expect the model to
be able to pick it up as it's being
implemented?  Yes, there are several
different explanations.  One is that
we expect the models to arrive
soon, but they haven't yet.
So why not leverage these
skills during training?
Another is that we don't focus on making it
really good at the job of
widespread implementation.  We just
want it to be really good in RSI
.  And this is simply a way to
generate revenue in order to
reinvest it in a model that is
capable of doing an excellent job
in developing RSI;  And then,
once the singularity occurs, what
comes out on the other side will be really
good in all the things that seem like
bottlenecks for the
current generation of models.  I don't know if you have
any idea about how, how much I can
learn, why there is so much
task-specific knowledge in
these models if the path is like this
kind of generalization.
Yes. I mean, if the models
were good enough at
learning in context, then, in
theory, they wouldn't need
financial training; they'd simply be
able to figure it out, read
all the books on the fly, and
work out how to do everything in the
appropriate jurisdiction.  Yes, and
you could argue that you need to do a
lot of this domain-specific training
just to make them more
efficient.  So even if they were
smart enough to
work this out on the fly, you might
still want to do a
lot of water cooling and bake all these
intuitions into the weights.  Therefore, the
model would be more efficient in
runtime.
Yes.
Yes, I would say that in practice, it seems
that model providers go
domain by domain and try to
strengthen models in the
highest value domain.  And I would say that's one
of the answers to why the
models have improved so much.  It's
simply because
model providers have covered many of the
high-value domains and the
most common skill types.  I mean
, I think another thing is that it's not that
expensive to do both things at the same
time, right?  Because the models
are huge, they can
easily afford to learn everything in terms of their
parameters.  And there is
likely to be some transfer,
even if finances are not
specifically important to the
RSI information.  The
general meta-learning of how
to figure out what is important, how to
have taste, how to do a
long-term job is potentially
generalizable.  And there isn't that much
RSI data in the world, by the
way.  It is a little difficult to
generate and, moreover, it requires a
lot of effort.  So, if you can
amortize this other data, get
some transfer value from it, you already
have a lot of
compute space and parameters, so
why not do it?  In addition, of course,
to the direct commercial incentive of
selling your own
business model.
Yes, that makes sense.
Well, yes, I will add that, well, there is
a doubt as to whether this current paradigm
of doing something like simulation to
reality will be the dominant one
forever.  Basically, you look at what
real-world tasks are like and then
try to create a bunch of environments
that can be simulated, like in the
data center, and you can do real-world simulation in
them.  And I think that, obviously, this has been
very successful, but it has many
weaknesses because many things are
difficult to simulate, especially if they
involve interacting with a lot of
humans in real time.  Yes,
therefore there are some doubts about
whether Sim-to-Real will remain the
dominant framework forever.
I think Sim-to-Real has to be the
dominant framework, while the
efficiency of samples is low
because right now you need thousands and
thousands of interactions with humans and
no human is going to sit there and
deal with this, basically being the
RL training cycle.
Yes. So
now we had to simulate that to
get the samples you need,
but obviously if the efficiency of the
samples improves a lot, you would expect
learning from
implementation to become a
much bigger part.
Although there are other things
you could do, such as learning outside of
politics so you don't take all the
leads, and even without simulating
everything again, you can potentially learn
something from them.
Jane Street has just launched a new
competition and it is the most ambitious one yet
.  Design an
ASIC protocol emulator.  Basically, if you have
a chip you want to test, you can
connect it to this ASIC and then this
ASIC will simulate realistic traffic.
That way you can see how the
chip responds without having to connect it to a
live system.  Jane Street seeks
flexible, general-purpose designs
, not single-protocol emulators
.  When I spoke with them, they
suggested that I start by trying to
implement what are apparently
three very common protocols: UART, SPI,
and I2C.  Jane Street also mentioned
that they expected the more
ambitious designs to also address USB and
low-speed Ethernet, and any
other protocols that would make
your chip's specific architecture more flexible.  It's
important that your design is
reprogrammable instead of having to
implement a bunch of
specific protocols on a chip.  If a
new protocol comes out after your ASIC
is ready, your chip should still be
able to handle it.  Exactly how you do it is up
to you, but there is one
strict restriction.  Your design should
target an open-source 130nm process node
.  This is because
Jane Street will pay to record the
most innovative submissions and send
physical copies to the winners.  The
competition is open until
January 18, 2027, and
teamwork is strongly recommended.
Go to janestreet.com/sworc ash to
download the template code and
get started.  I want to ask more about
this because it's a bit strange that 50%
of the computer's time is spent
on inference and doesn't
directly help improve the model.  One
of the key advantages I would expect
digital minds to have is
that, unlike a human who
has 50 years of
real-world experience, a model will experience,
through all its instances, I don't know
, millions of years of implementation
in all kinds of economically
relevant work in the economy.  And right now,
that data doesn't help the model
improve significantly.  It seems so
obvious that, over time, the
models should be able to learn from
this data, and once they do,
you'd have something that would almost feel
like a burst of
widely deployed intelligence because the
model is assimilating so much
information across all these
deployed instances.  But when do you expect
this kind of hive-mind madness to start happening
?
Think broadly, as if
this is already happening at a very basic level
, right?  As in the
next generation of models.  Right now
you can always take your
implementation data and put it into
the pre-training or
intermediate phase of future models.
Especially if you do some kind of
filtering or some kind of judgment or
annotation or a recent synthesis of
it.  To
what extent do you think that explains the
improvement from generation to generation?
It explains quite a bit.  I mean,
especially, I don't know if the
labs do this because, in
theory, they claim that they don't train with
people's data.  But the
Chinese do it 100% and
definitely gain this advantage,
obviously, by implementing it.
Basically, this is what
distillation is: they take over
the models, get some of their
implementation data, get a
fraction of that by pinging the
model, and then train the next
generation of models on it. And
suddenly they can do it on their
own models too; there's no reason
not to.
I completely agree with this
.  I think if you step back far enough,
this is definitely happening.
As you can imagine, and we all
imagine that this is what
continuous learning is, the holy grail, it's
like this very, very organic live cycle
of an individual model
getting a live experience and
update in the moment and
learning from it.  And many things
break down when you approach that level of
granularity, but yes, the big
labs are doing this, like
closed models, they are
doing it.  There are also
early signs that people are using
open-source models, and doing so at
a much faster pace.  So,
a good example is probably
Composer.  Um, you have some kind of
model and you're able to, or like, you
know, Harvey is doing the same thing
with legal agents.  It's like you're getting
very specific environments from the data
you have for that particular task
and things that, you know,
users complain about.  And like all the
feedback you somehow
extract from your
specific implementations, many of these companies
have the advantage over the big
labs in that they can use this
data very, very well.  Yes. And then
they will create environments.  They'll like, you
know, doing a great
Kimmy K3 post-workout.  They
will implement it.  They could also do
some online learning, like
Composer did online, basically
like reinforcing over a long period of time.
Well, yes, there's still a human in
the circuit.  There's still a human
saying, "Well, these are the
signals that matter to us. This is how
we're going to create environments from the
data we have."  And then it's like a
longer cadence than you might
be thinking, but it's really
happening.  And over time that
circuit will get faster and
faster.    I mean, the
Composer thing is
interesting because here's where the
model, like in Cursor, shows people either
pressing the Tab key or not pressing it
on the next completion that
the model suggests.  And based on that,
Cursor improves every day at
predicting the next user.
That was the old Tab model.  They did
exactly the same thing for the
actual generative model, not just for the
Tab model, but for the other one as well.
Interesting.
And it was difficult because when you do
online reinforcement learning, you don't
have groups, right?  You just have one
user saying one thing and then
you get an implementation.  And
then you have a big
variance reduction problem.  And
Cursor's somewhat vague response to this was
something like: "Oh, you know, we have very
good heuristics that are able to
estimate, for example, how much better than
average this response was or how much
worse than average this response was."
And then they would do something like a big
booster update, and then their
solution for knowing if it was getting worse or not
was something like: if it improved in
Cursor Bench, they would implement the new
model every 5 hours, and if it didn't,
they would discard that version.
Interesting.
Yes, I think your biggest problem is
really just not knowing what
the reward function
for natural data should be, and if you use
some kind of surface signal like
whether they accepted the code or the edit,
the reward might somehow be hacked
.
But does this seem to be a
bigger problem with simulation in reality
, where the longer the
task horizon, the harder it
is to simulate them within a
data center?  It seems to me that, at least
potentially in coding,
we are reaching a point where there is
no
year-long coding assignment that doesn't
require talking to a client or
interacting with the company or
interacting with users.  And if
you think about the range of things we would
like AI to be able to
do, you want a
superintelligence to eventually be able to run
a business or start a new business and
make it profitable, or have a profitable day trading operation
in the markets, or win a
lawsuit.  And all of these are things that are
very difficult to simulate in a
data center.  As if an inherent part
of learning were interacting with
the real world, perhaps they need to
learn how to improve in these areas, such as
transferring the simulation to the
real world.  But on the other hand,
you might need significant updates
to these types of interactions to
improve them.  And if that's the case,
if the transfer isn't
strong enough and requires
updating the weights, then the fact
that the models are so
inefficient with the samples is
perhaps a deeper problem.  And the
reason I'm curious about
this is that I feel like, by default, I don't
see how we won't get some kind of
recursive madness from the previous event
in the next 10 years.  But the
only reason that might not
happen is because of
weight updates;  The sampling efficiency of these
seems to still be far behind that
of humans, right?  Possibly
a million times behind
humans in terms of the amount of
data we use from
birth to adulthood compared
to what a model processes from its
initial cold start to the end of its
training.  And so, yes, all
this is to say, first of all, is there going to be
a good transfer
between simulations and really
complicated,
extremely long-horizon things that we want
AI to do in the real world?  And if not, does
that really mean that the
efficiency of the actual sample in these
models will hurt us?
I think, perhaps, the way
I would break down the two types of tasks where
models improve and
models that will continue to have
problems is whether the task is cumulative
or if you have to have this
non-stationary distribution, you have to
keep learning and, so to
speak, relitigating a lot
of things.  For example, RSA could be
an example of a cumulative task.  In
theory, it is possible to have a
Python file with less than one
million tokens that trains
a model from scratch which is capable of
performing a recursive self-improvement process
.  And every discovery
you make is a kind of line in
the sand that you maintain.  For example, if it
is true that, for RSI, we do not need to
discover a new variant of
care or whatever.  For example,
once you've discovered
attention and then once you've
discovered, you know, a mix of
experts, once you discover GRPO, you
just add it to the
training stack and that's it.  And a good
example of this is, you know, the
old 5.6 training, the 5.6 terol
, whatever OpenAI has
instructed it to train.  As if I didn't have to
go back and rediscover
the attention.  As if it
had basically called a bunch of scripts
like pre-training.sh and pre-training.sh
and just done that.  So that's
an example of a
cumulative task.  I think the real world, and
the reason why people think so much
about continuous learning, is that it's
not actually a cumulative task
.  Imagine that in a
law firm you have an agent who acts
as a legal associate.  It is a
very non-stationary distribution.
You have to be able to fit into your
context all the relationships between
all the important people in that
company, which also change all the
time.  Yes. You have all these
implicit ways of knowing how
things are done, where to find information,
etc.  And that's not as clear an example
of cumulative tasks as RSI is.
Well, I think there will be a break
between tasks.  But, you know, if
labs realize that and
believe that RSI is cumulative in the
sense that we don't need to go back
and discover something new, like the
architecture or whatever, then
maybe they'll focus more and more effort
and calculations on that instead of...
It's a shame that RSI turned out to
be easier than
transfer learning.
Yes. I
don't know if you have any
opinion on this.
Yes, I would say that there are...
current models are weaker than
humans in many different ways,
and some of them might have to
do with sample efficiency in
a given regime.  I mean,
in some regimes, models are
very efficient in sampling, such as
contextual learning;  But then there
might be some
average length regime where they are less
efficient in the sample because
humans can do some kind of
weight update more
efficiently than the models.  Well, I think
being less efficient at
sampling in certain regimes could
be one of the sources of weakness,
but then I think there are other sources
of weakness that are completely
different from that.  For example, having
less diversity of thought than
humans or, yes, being bad at certain
types of long-term judgments.  I mean
, I think a lot of what
people call taste is something about
behavior that works in the long
run, and that people have realized
works in the long run.  Not everything,
but some aspects of taste,
especially for something like
software engineering, I think a large
part of the taste is about which
systems will be
maintainable and will
work well in the long term in this
project.  So yes, the
weaknesses of humans, which limit
the RSI along with other things, are...yes
, yes, there are a variety of them and
some of them are related
to sample efficiency and others are
not.
Perhaps an interesting thought experiment
would be, for example, if
you could give a model, for example
, a context window of, I don't know, a
billion tokens, or whatever,
you would have to have included your
experience prior to, say, RLHF, and,
as if it had all that experience in
the context window, it would have the
same sample efficiency and
context learning ability as with a
million tokens.  Do you think the taste issue
is resolved? Would it be able to make
the same judgments as you, or is something
fundamental missing besides a
longer context window with the same
sampling efficiency?
Yes, I mean, I would have to be
trained to learn from that
context.  So I'm not sure, either I
would have to be trained to
learn the correct update to
make from that context or I
would have to be trained to
learn how to
dump it all.  Like your whole life,
as a research experience?    I
mean, you still need the
data to train it in context, but
even if you could theoretically
get like a trillion times the amount of context,
you'd still need a trillion times the length
of data to train it, like right now
if you have like 100 T times that, I'm
just asking if you have that much.
Yes, theoretically I think so.  I mean,
this really boils down to the
question of how meta-learnable
taste is from
shorter-horizon episodes.  And I feel like there's no
obvious reason why it's so
long because humans
somehow develop a taste without having
many long episodes, like we don't
live to 10,000 or we, you
know, develop pretty
fast, right?  And then, you know
, if you think about the difference between a
first-year PhD student
and a postdoc or something, it's like
5 years, and they've only done 10, 15, 30
research projects in total,
but somehow they develop a
taste quite quickly from a
relatively short succession of
small things.  And so, in theory
, it is possible to develop it like that.
Obviously, AI will have much more
to develop taste, such as
meta-learning it, and then it's as if that
generalizes well to things with a
very long horizon.  I think that's the
question that I believe is really not
resolved at this point.  We don't
know.
Returning to this question, over
time there should be a system where
AIs learn a lot from each
individual implementation instance they
have.  Well, currently you
could say that there is a
meta-fuzzy process through which models
do inform from the
implementation, but I think it is a
very weak feedback loop.    Do
you see this on the horizon where there's
something like hive mind learning
that's very fast?  And if so
, how exactly does it happen?
Actually, I would say that in the future
we will have a hive mind that learns
from all its
implementation experience.  I mean, a big
part of it has to do with
incentives rather than a
technical issue.  Therefore, companies
will not want the
model provider to learn from their entire
implementation because that could
reduce their business advantage.
I think that perhaps the economics of this will not
necessarily push for
major upgrades to a large,
shared, common model, but rather to the
modules that are replaced.
Therefore, a very obvious example is this,
but it could be something else, like, you
know, a lot of work has been done to
try to fit an
arbitrary context length to a fixed size.
This is the whole thing about
linear attention and all that kind of stuff, like
cartridges, which are essentially
KB caches trained to be
very, very compressed KB caches so
that they can fit a lot of information.  That's
another example of, you know, something
that companies might be
willing to subscribe to if it's
substituted in the model and not like
actually changing the underlying base model itself
.  Therefore, there are
many different versions of
learning from your
real-time data, and the latest ones don't
really help large labs
because they are just these modules.  But I
think economic pressure will
force labs to take
that path first before they can
embark on this, you know.
So, what economic pressure is
there?  Because I feel that even if
you have a lot of cartridges or
lawyers or whatever, you can take
all these traces and distill all of
this for the pre-training of your
next generation of lawyers.
Yes. So, it may be a
more indirect form of learning that
the big labs are getting,
and it's obviously still
very valuable to them.  But I can't
imagine a world where
we start with something like, you know,
let's just train this big
model directly with all the exact data we
have.
No, I think it will definitely go
through stages because, I mean, this
assumes it's just a
discontinuous event where we suddenly
fix, like,
heavyweight updates continuously, and in practice,
I think it's much more likely that
cartridges and things like that will allow you to
specialize in the implementation.
Then you generate traces and put them into your
model.  About three months later,
you manage to create the model that is better at
this kind of thing.  You specialize it
again and consolidate it again.  And
eventually we'll make this leap faster and faster
, so instead of launching a
model every 3 months, it's now every
week, then every day, and then every
hour, at which point we'll have basically
solved it.
Yes. And I think this is also a
good point because you asked how far we
are from the current paradigm of being
able to do this.  I think we've
done a little research
on this, and other people have done
quite a bit of research on a
really large scale.  For example,
when you remove enough noise and
have large enough patches
, this external looping process
of putting data into
intermediate training, creating external environments,
works as a kind of
continuous learning regime.  But the
problem is that, when you get close
enough to a micro level, it's as if
I had a model and I was
trying to update it again for, say
, a law firm or
something like that.  And I try to do it
very continuously, as with real data, or at
least more recent data.  All methods
break down a little.  Therefore, if
I do an SFT of the model, I'm just, you
know, successfully tracking, outside of
politics, inside of politics,
like, finally, in the very
iterative regime, like when you're doing, you
know, hundreds of, like, these
micro-updates, you see so many
catastrophic forgettings;  You see forgetfulness of, for
example, previous information
I learned about the base model that
was there long before, and I see degradation
of general usability capabilities.  You
know, just the distillation of
policies seems to push
this horizon a little, but it still
ultimately succumbs to the same thing.  Well,
RL isn't very good at that; it's good at
acquiring capabilities, but it
's not as good at acquiring knowledge,
and only this very explicit
kind of knowledge, like, well, how this person does
this at this law firm, and this
is a very specific process that
we found, and you have to put a lot of
computing power into creating the
right environments to acquire the knowledge
in the model.  Do
you think the fundamental problem here
, why you're getting worse in these other
skills or having lapses and things like that,
is fundamentally a
problem of ability or is it a problem
of techniques?
A little bit of both.  I believe that SFT and
even simple
policy distillation can be too
destructive.  The reason why
RL is so favorable is because it changes
a very, very small amount of the
model, and there is a great deal of
evidence that explains why
this happens.  So you just modify it
by this very, very, very small loss value
to bring it to the
right point.  Well, that also limits what
you can do with
machine learning, like how much you can
actually change the model.
Whereas what you're saying is
that the reason this is
potentially a winner-takes-
all is that it's very difficult to summarize
so much information in the base model
without ruining something in the new interface.
Yes. It's easy to summarize it in a
different base model.  This is where I think it's
mainly about technique.  It's not
that there isn't capacity.  If you had
a model with all this data and
you took a model of almost the same
size and pre-trained it from scratch
with all this material in the
pre-training, it would be better.  And I think that's a
lot of what's
happening today.  Therefore, it
is very similar to a bottleneck
that prevents us from continuing to train the
same model forever instead of
simply obtaining all the data from the
old model and training a new
model from scratch.  And this is
exactly as Joey says, like a
combination of plasticity and
catastrophic forgetting.  And then, you know, if you
naively train with non-
stationary data because you keep adding
new data as you go along,
basically this is altering the
distribution of the data, so that
the old data gets forgotten.  And we
really don't have good methods
to prevent that from happening.
And then perhaps, at the limit, like
a bottleneck, perhaps by
retraining the model from scratch with
all this information.
Yes, which, of course, is very expensive
.  Training the model from scratch is expensive
.
But you're going to do it anyway.    I mean,
not necessarily.  I mean that
perhaps, over time, if you've continued
learning, you'll never train a
new model.  You simply have a model that
keeps learning and keeps working,
right?    There
may be some deep technical reason
why it's so difficult
because of these...That's
a good question.  That's a good
question.
I think we've delayed how much
we have to do from scratch.  As if it
were now definitely possible to
take the pre-trained base and do some
very good intermediate training on top of
that, continuously, plus some
continuous learning from different
checkpoints that are further along
in the training;  And that
seems more like continuous learning,
but it's certainly not the case of, you
know, taking the latest model,
applying a couple of very
small updates, and iteratively never
losing it.  But isn't this it?  I'm
a little confused because isn't this
literally what happens during
training or during
post-training or something like that?
You simply have a model that has already
gone through a lot of training and then
you distill some fork that has been
subjected to more
continuous learning or something like that.  Isn't that
literally what happens? And why
is that bad?
Even on a large enough scale
, I think you're eliminating a lot of the
noise.  And as if you weren't
just focusing on one distribution,
which as Brian said is like, you know,
that's very... If you're just focusing
on one task, right?  Like that assignment
...
Oh, right.  And I mean, in the
final regime, you'd be doing... I don't
know, there are billions of
instances implemented.  You're kind of
learning from all of them at once.  And
so, hopefully, there will be some
noise cleaning and that kind of thing,
right?
Perhaps that scale, yes.
Yes, I mean, I think
you can definitely, as I was saying,
do continuous mid-
course training for a long time and you can go
back to a checkpoint given
the mid-course training data
.  But at the same time, you can't
do this indefinitely.  If you keep
continuing halfway with the
same base forever, it's like it will become
asymptotic at some point.  You can't
just learn
new things on that basis.  And that's why
people end up training new bases.
Otherwise, you'd still be using the same base
halfway through training every time.
Whenever I finish recording an
interview, I immediately dump all
my thoughts into Slack.  Things like,
what was the most interesting thing?  "And what
should be cut. This ensures
my editors have all the context they
need to start editing the
episode. But it's not like these
dumps of information have
clear timestamps, and my
unedited recordings are many
hours long. It can take a lot of the editor's time
just to find the
exact moments I was
referencing. So we decided to try
adding a Grock bot producer to
our chat. And now, whenever one
of my editors posts a draft of the
episode, the Grock bot opens the
transcript on its own computer and
starts working. Usually,
even before I see the message.
It takes the notes I left in Slack and
highlights the relevant bits in the
transcript. It also uses a
large archive of cases I've compiled
with all my preferences, so it can
suggest potential edits. And when it's
done, it sends me its top
clip candidates, so I can
review everything from my phone. This
has worked really well. Being able to send
informal messages as if I
were texting
my editor, and have the transcript
immediately reflect my preferences,
has been a huge help. Try Grockbot
yourself at  x.ai/bot. Okay, let's talk
a little bit about data now. Well,
I'm generally interested in this question of
how much of AI progress is
explained solely by the progress of
data. It doesn't mean it's necessarily going to be
difficult to automate,
but that's our question. So, is
there some data distribution that
, if trained on
current architectures, would result in a
superintelligence that
completely dominates human experts in
every field? Are
we talking about pre-
training and post-
training data, like environments as well?
I think the existence of this is obvious
. It's as if we could create the
right environment.
Yes, I mean, in the trivial case,
we could train it to generate
the Python file that trains the
actual superintelligence. Simply
by having it memorize the weights. Yes,
there's probably a ladder of real-
world environments that could be
built so that you get an
AI researcher that's at least as
good as a human researcher, but
the effort of climbing each
successive rung grows exponentially. And
those are going to be the two questions you'll have
that we have to weigh to determine
how quickly we're going to reach that
final step where the
situation is finally better. I think
that's pretty clear. And I think
, you know, we're still
relatively at the beginning of
creating our own environment.
There are a lot of asymmetries that we exploit
to create good environments. So,
one of those asymmetries we
talked about earlier is that there are environments where it's
easier to go back
and forth. And what I
mean by that is that it's very easy to
define this complex
data generation process. And this is like
a kind of latent variable that
you keep hidden from the model. You can
generate arbitrarily
complex environments, and the model has to do a
lot of irreducible token expenditure and
irreducible work to figure out
what that data generation process was
. There are asymmetries in terms of
how, you know, you can inject
real-world information. For
example, Anthropic finds a bug
through tens of thousands of
combined human and LLM hours and
turns it into a very, very
tidy environment that, in theory, a single LLM
could find with a few  A few
million tokens. So,
there are all these SM problems that
we're selecting, and we're counting on
this generalization of the
task horizon. But I think, yes, again,
this is just going to have
diminishing returns at some
point. At some point, the
diminishing returns are due to how
difficult it is to create these environments in the
first place. Like, how to devise them, because you can't
always have those processes where it's
much easier to go
backward than
forward. In fact, you have to
sit down and build something that,
with humans, you know, a
long enough time horizon, is going to be a really
complex task to create. And then there are also going to be
time and computation bottlenecks for
the agent to perform those tasks. Well,
I think you'll just start to see
this curve flatten out.
I saw something about how someone fitted the
Toki model, which is only trained on
data up to 1930, on this
modern coding agent data, and it
performed better than Claude 3 Opus on
SweetBench. This model, which doesn't have
any  Code knowledge can be
fine-tuned with a moderate amount of
data and behave better as a
coding agent than this
much larger, pre-trained model. It's
crazy. And it shows you that once
you have an example of the
correct expert behavior, it's surprisingly
easy to copy it into a
relatively weak model.
Yes. But a counterexample of that kind
is that there was a paper
recently. They trained it up to
fifth-grade math. Yes.
And elementary English and
stuff. It was a decent language model,
and they tried to apply it to
machine learning for
late high school and
college math, but the gap was
too big. They couldn't get it to go up at
all. But if
you did successive sets of
seventh-grade math and then
eighth-grade math, you could go up to level
12. So again, it's like, what
's the distance between the rungs of
those ladders, and how hard is it to
create them?
Yes, and this brings us back to the
RL signal problem.
Machine learning isn't very good at
exploration right now. So if the
model can't get 128 rewards
, it's very unlikely to get
signals for  to progress. That's why
we use curricula in reinforcement learning
. Whereas in
pre-training we don't, because it does
n't pose any problems for
pre-training.
Yes, and I repeat,
pre-training data is different from
post-training data. And I imagine that as
we move forward, yes, humans will be
involved less and less, but
that doesn't change the fact that the
bottleneck is the amount of signal that
can be extracted from the real world.
So, there's a lot of signal in the world, and
that's true. For example, there are people
doing spreadsheet tasks,
people doing legal tasks, and all
that kind of stuff. But, you know, the
capability frontier of where
the models are now—that is, how many
bits of the world are actually relevant
to improving the model's capabilities
? For example, how many
new math problems are being
solved that couldn't be solved or
are beyond the scope or
understanding of current models?
For example, how many
new coding problems are being created
or solved that are beyond the
scope of current models? And,  For
example, I think that's why
diminishing returns come into play,
because even the world as a
whole doesn't give you the bits that are useful
to take you to the next level of
capability. Yes.
I totally agree with that.
It's like a question of where
the signal is coming from. And the signal isn't, you know, in
pre-training the signal is already there
in Common Crawl, right? Like for
the tasks you're interested in during
pre-training. The problem is that you don't
just get the signal, you
filter out all the noise that's there. And it's
a fairly automatable process, but
as the models improve
during the mid- and late-
training stages, the signal simply isn't there
in the original data
we have. No amount of filtering
will get this, you know, there's no
hidden evidence of the Millennium Prize Problem
in Common Crawl. We could
just filter until we see it
, right? And then, at that point,
you have to get bits out of it
somehow: either from humans, like,
directly, by asking them to write out
their reasoning, or, like, by creating
environments where, like,  Humans
decide, like, what environment should be
created, what the goals of
these environments are, or, like, you know,
some kind of, like, training on,
like, the human data that exists in
the implementation. Like, you have to
get the bits from somewhere.
Yes. Yes. There is a question of how much of the
progress in pretraining is
being driven by the data.
Yes.
I did this research with Jerry Han,
who is a student at Princeton, where
we basically trained all the
recipes from 2019 to now in
pairs with all the datasets
from 2019 to now. So, you
're training like GPT-2 on the
newest dataset, like
Ultrafine Web, and you train Delphi, which
is the newest training recipe
, or the open-source training recipe
, on Pile or some
older dataset, and you do like,
the whole grid, and you see how you
get to a certain level of capabilities;
how much less processing is needed
on this grid? And you see that the
data seems to explain like 9 times the
computational efficiency gain,
but improvements in architecture
explain like  3x the
computational efficiency gain at a
very small scale. And to the extent that's
true at a large scale, that
most
pre-training computational efficiency gains
come from better data, how long
can that continue? Can you keep
filtering data more and more and creating
more and more synthetic data until
...? Yes, do you have any idea how much further
pre-training progress can continue
with
pre-disclosure?
I think my previous hypothesis is that,
again, the ripe fruit is somewhat
exhausted; for example, we have the
internet as this big block, and it's not
as if the internet is
necessarily growing at the same rate that
all the useful things
within the internet are
growing at the same time. So
, we probably have a
bunch of 0.1% loss drops
to go, but definitely
not as many as have occurred
so far. Yes. But it's also very
interesting that, as you know,
you find this cumulative improvement of
27x in both. I think it was Epoch or
someone who estimated it as three times a
year since 2019.  which would imply
something like three to the seventh power, like
over 2000.
Yes. As a times improvement, so
where's that missing? That
hundredfold improvement, or whatever it
comes from, probably gives you a
good indication of how much of this is
really a product of
post-training.
I think the explanation has to be
that a lot of
computational efficiency gains are
scale-dependent, and we're starting at an
extremely small scale, and that raises
the question of whether
data computational efficiency gains or
algorithmic computational efficiency gains are more
scale-dependent. I don't know if you guys have any
prior insight into that. We just didn't
have enough computers to
investigate that question. I
mean, naively, in
theory, the scale dependence of
architecture is pretty well known, and you
can fit a straight line to it,
whereas I wouldn't have any idea
how to do that to combine the
pre-training, post-training, and
intermediate data.
I like data to be more
important. I think architectures
are like one-off things, like an
architect. I think combining, like,
say, an efficiency gain of X
% is a bit misleading because  What
an architecture does is allow you to
reach a qualitatively
new regime that you couldn't reach with the
previous architecture. And then, within
that regime, obviously, the data
is the main thing that determines it. But
, if we say it doesn't have, like GQA,
where we were doing a
full-time day, we couldn't do
a million; it would be ridiculously expensive to
do a million contexts. And because
of that, we could never use the data,
which is actually like a million
contexts. And therefore,
we couldn't get these capabilities,
although if you just do something naive, like
how much this does in a 2K context
where the architecture doesn't unlock
anything, then the data, you know, would
look a lot more important than it actually
is, right? It's not
clear to me that these things are
really multiplicative gains in
this sense.
Yes. I see. But then, what's
the takeaway about the
scale dependence of the data? I mean,
as far as
scale dependence is concerned, I think a
lot of the
mid- and post-training data we have
now improves with scale because a
lot of  They, like the
very long context horizon of
hardware, really require
large models to be usable.
Yes, yes.
And this isn't, you know, if you try to
train your 100-million-
parameter model on three
reference traces, it won't get you
anywhere; it won't show you the same kind of
improvement you'd get if you trained a
real-world, sensible model on it
.
Yes.
And now it's also difficult because
many of the architectural changes,
like those in Chimera, for example, or
DeepSeek, are making these
architectural modifications not only by
eliminating pre-training
memory loss, but also, for example, in
how the models are going to be used in
the real world. So, yes,
inference efficiency, like having
some form of compressed attention in
DeepSeek models, isn't
necessarily geared toward, you know,
this is fundamentally as a
pre-training improvement.  "It's
like, well, we're considering how
the models are going to be used.
Right, right, right.
Well, one question that interests me
to understand the future is how
parameter scaling will develop as we move
into a more intensive
machine learning regime. I know, I don't know
how fast historically. Yes,
you can look at
open-source architectures and see how fast
the parameters have been scaling, and
maybe it's about twice a
year for
frontier open-source models. And to the extent
that even
frontier closed-source models have like 100 billion or
200 billion active parameters. Do you think it
holds at twice a year,
or is there another
winning machine learning regime where you also
want to conserve computation in
implementations, and maybe there's
a threshold effect where you have
enough capacity? And at that point, arbitrarily
increasing the parameters
doesn't matter as much? Do
you have any idea how many
active parameters a frontier model will have
in 2030?
Yes, I think for the next few
years we're going to be, like, because
we're very focused on..."  Making
increasingly longer implementations
for machine learning, where
inference efficiency is very
important. Yes. It seems that the models
aren't necessarily saturated in
that sense. The bottleneck is
still the environments. And we
might see a small plateau.
I have a feeling that, you know,
Methos and GPT models are much
smaller than, you know, the 10
trillion parameter range that
people talk about. Even
naively comparing them to open-source models
, you can probably
retract that conclusion. Well,
yes, I probably would
n't foresee a
huge increase in the number of
parameters for the next few years. But again, there are many
different things to trade off here;
you decide the size of your model based on the
amount of
pre-training data you have, and then
the difficulty of the
machine learning environments you have to
train on. And ideally, you want to
reach an optimum point where, you
know, you can get a
decent pass in one or something like that in the
harder environments you have. And, so to
speak, it wouldn't make sense to
make a bigger model pass
there because  Then you'd just
be paying, so to speak, for a
lot more inference failures than
you need. Well, there are a lot of
inputs to this. It depends on how
quickly, you know, Mcore and then
internally these guys can scale
the complexity of the RL environments they're
training in.
Hmm. I would expect the models to
keep growing just because
people are scaling compute and
GPUs are getting bigger and bigger, but
I would say exactly how much they grow
depends a bit on the laws of
scaling in non-obvious ways. So
, one thing is that I think
data efficiency is going to be a
bigger driver than the
compute efficiency of the
exact architectures people are using
now that we're getting to the point where we're
running out of
high-quality pre-training data
. So, that could affect
how sparse you want to make the
model. And I also think we don't really
understand scarcity. It's
like parameters are a
different resource than
active parameters, but it's like scarcity
has definitely increased a
bit, but it's not  Of course, it's not going to
keep increasing without limit. There might
be some kind of optimum point.
There's an argument that scarcity
should worsen
data efficiency because you might have to
learn the same thing from several experts.
Although that's debatable. So, I
think we don't have a
good enough theory of the laws of
scaling to really understand
why scarcity helps, to what extent it will
help, and whether it will stabilize at
some point at a certain level of
scarcity.
And—I'm sorry, but can you explain
exactly what the
implications of
data efficiency would be for…? Well, it sounds like you'd
say, "Well, there should be less
scarcity."  But what are the
other implications of
parameter scaling?
I suppose the scaling law simply
doesn't necessarily seek the
maximum; it doesn't try to optimize the
computer's efficiency.  Therefore,
you have all the options you can
choose in the architecture and each of
them gives you a
different scaling law and
you would generally consider some kind of
computation-based envelope.
Therefore, you would consider performance
versus computation and take the
envelope of the best models.  But
, if we make that decision based
on the data, it's as if we're assuming
we can spend a lot of computing power, and
therefore the data is on
our x-axis instead of on the
computing axis.  Then, we obtain a
different set of optima or a
different set of models that
are on that frontier.
Yes. And I also don't think we've necessarily
doubled the size of
the models every year over the
last few years.  For example, people
have been training 1
trillion parameter models for at least
some years.  There was even an
open-source one called Falcon, but
Liam from Periodic Labs, I think,
tweeted yesterday about how an
early experiment on OpenAI was like
training a 1 trillion
parameter model that was very, very sparse.
Oh yes, that's what they did before
OpenAI.  That was like in Google
Switch Transformer, yeah.
Yes. So, he was like, you know, very,
very good at knowledge, but
terrible at reasoning because he was so
scattered.  And so, yes, it seems we've been
playing in this range of
100 billion to 2 trillion
parameters for at least a while.
And it certainly hasn't been this pleasant
linear increase, yes.    I mean
, I feel like there are two things.
As Charlie said,
inference efficiency is very important for
RL implementations.  And so it
will really reduce the
active parameters quite a bit.  And then I think
the overall parameters also
depend a lot on the hardware.
Therefore, it is necessary to obtain a
very high memory bandwidth and a
VRAM size in order to serve
multimillion-parameter models.  And so, right now
, people continue to
use a large number of
H100 devices and similar ones.  And as
everyone migrates to GB,
their tapes will have greater capacity
to scale, serve, and efficiently perform
large-scale RL inferences
at much
larger scales.  The issue of data
is interesting, I think, because, naively
, larger models are much
more efficient in terms of sampling
real data points.  And
therefore, even if the model doesn't become saturated
, it's still better to make it
bigger because larger models
generalize better and achieve
better loss for the same amount
of data.  Therefore, right now
I think we have a lot of data and that's not
the restriction, but the calculation.
Therefore, we have smaller models
that are very influential and
efficient.  But, if computers are
no longer the bottleneck, it could
return to larger models that
are somewhat undersaturated, but have
this generalization capacity
because they are much larger.
If you only observe
Chinchilla's basic scaling law and maximize the
parameters, then
yes.  In
reality, it only slightly reduces the
amount of data you need to
achieve the same loss.
Yes.
If you go to infinity in the parameters,
the amount of data you need
decreases by less than 10x.
Mhm.
Simply due to the nature of the
power law.
But now we're on the
data-heavy side of Chinchilla's laws
, right?  So, right now
we're overtraining the models that are
put into Chinchilla and we could
easily return to a point
where, as we run out of
data, we go back to the
Chinchilla optimum.  We're even a little bit on
the overtraining side, you
know, of the undertraining model.
But surely, even with these
new chips coming onto the market and all that
, since we're going to have so many
computing bottlenecks
over the next few years, that won't
necessarily be the case.    It
could be...Yes, this depends on the
ratio you have between
training and
computational inference.  It's as if you have a
major bottleneck in the data, not
the computational one; you should
increase it.  If you have a major
computational bottleneck, you
should always reduce it.  And then yes,
but you can also use
synthetic, computer-generated data.
So it's like one of those things that are very
difficult to predict.
Yes, I think part of the reason why it
took people so long to discover
the laws of scaling in the first
place was that if you don't do all these
things right, then you don't get such a
clear relationship.  And the beautiful
straight lines in the graphs
hide a lot of complexity about how to
ensure you scale each
hyperparameter correctly or
parameterize your optimizer in a
way that scales and where you don't have to
change your hyperparameters as
you change the size of the model.
And errors have their own
clear scaling laws, right?
Like, you know, like with Kaplan and
forgetting about cosine annealing or
even just not considering the
embedding parameters, I think.  And
that ruined the estimation of
smaller models because the
embedding parameters are a decent
model size.
A little bit about RL.  So, I feel like
a year ago, a lot of people were
arguing that RL wouldn't be very
successful in scaling models.  I think
John, you wrote a
research article where you pointed out that
models learn one bit per episode
when you do RL.  Basically, they learn:
"Did I give the correct answer or was I
wrong?"  And I wrote a few
blog posts earlier
this year.  I thought, "It's even worse than
that because when the
approval rate is low and
the model is very unlikely to give the
correct answer, it learns almost nothing from an
episode of real-life behavior."  But nowadays
I look at the models and they seem quite
intelligent, and it appears to be the result
of expanding machine learning.
Baron, I think
you posted something a few weeks ago in which you tried to
explain what's going on.  But
why has machine learning been
more successful than one
might naively think?
I believe the success of
machine learning is due to many things.
Firstly, I think that
intermediate training is slightly underestimated.  Therefore,
much of what we consider
machine learning successes
actually comes from
very, very good intermediate training data
, which is where
we basically do the pre-training, but
with synthetic reasoning data and
the kind of environments that allow the
model to start working for
machine learning.  Therefore,
this brings the model almost 80% of the
way to the final
machine learning checkpoint.  And, furthermore
, what
machine learning does is significantly alter
policy.  And well, this is one of the
reasons why it doesn't need as many
bits as you might naively think.    You do
n't have to learn all these
behaviors from scratch.  You only
need a few bits of these
episodes, which you do get.  And then,
the other thing I really point out in
my blog is that these bits are
actually an extremely high signal
compared to normal pre-training
, which is why
you need RL instead of just SFT on
successful reasoning traces.
Because they are exactly the bits about
how to get the right answer.
Well, there are two things.  So yes,
one is exactly the bits about how to
get the correct answer, but it's not
exactly how you think
because in SFT you have a trace,
right?  You have like a lot of
mathematical reasoning and then the
answer at the end.  The bit is still there,
as if you were still doing SFT on the
response token.  So, that bit is
still there.  The important thing is that the
target ignores all other bits.
So, in SFT you have, you know, ways
to try to match the
exact reasoning tokens that
the model produces.  Therefore, you're
basically getting
too much information about the exact way
this other model you
're training on reasons.  For RL
you only get one bit, and that means
this signal is not drowned out by the noise of
all the other bits in the
model.
Yes, yes.
And that's what it really is, a
super drastic increase in the
signal-to-noise ratio during
training, which is why
RL is so drastically efficient
in terms of steps.
Mhm.  And do you have any opinion
on that?  Yes, I like it. There's been a
lot of debate about what RL does to the
model compared to, you know,
mid-training or SFT or
whatever.  And, you know, everyone's talking
about how, you know, passing by one
will increase, but passing by 256
will decrease.  As if the
very rare traces of correct reasoning were
diminishing and being overtaken by a
gradient signal of an easier type of
reasoning traces.  And I
think the simplest way to look at
RL now is that if you have a
large enough amount of computation to sample a
group size large enough that
your probability of getting a
lot of correct answers is like
beyond a non-
negligible probability, then it will be weighted.
And, going back to Ben's point,
basically halfway through training
and, you know, more pre-training,
like the pass in one, the
starting point for RL, as you scale up on a
logarithmic number of
pre-training tokens.
Can I ask some very
basic questions?  I suppose that answer
makes sense, and perhaps there is
empirical research that
shows that this is what is
happening.  But then I just look at the
models themselves and I don't know what
happened.  So, maybe you can
give me some insight into
the basis of AI progress over
the past year.  But, if it is
yes, perhaps I'm just weighing up the
policies that were going to make the
right thinking anyway.
But, it seems that, qualitatively, the
models have become much more
capable.  And anyway, there may be
nothing, no
inherent contradiction there.  But
how can we scare the square, given
the relatively small impact
this would have on the RL,
based on the actual qualitative capabilities
the model seems to be
acquiring?
Therefore, one thing I want to
point out here is that it doesn't
necessarily imply that the RL has a
small effect, right?  Even if
you have a few bits and only change
the parameters a small amount,
the actual impact on the space of
functions that the model learns, such as
input-to-output mapping,
can still be very drastic.  You
know, even if it's like one bit
could change your function space a lot
and then discard
half of the hypothesis space.
Yes, yes.
Which is huge.  Therefore, I don't
think that's necessarily the case;
they are small amounts of bits,
small amounts of RL.  Once
you start from a really good point
, it means you don't have
drastic impacts on behavior.  At
least not necessarily.
I think it boils down to two things.  I think
the first thing is that everyone
expected turn-based learning to
generalize this reasoning across all
these different domains.  And I don't think we've
necessarily achieved
this horizontal generalization.
Training only in mathematics doesn't
necessarily make you the best
programmer.  It's like having to
apply RL in code environments.  I think what we did
achieve was a
generalization of horizon.
Yes. It's
as if the models learn to use
more tokens for longer periods and still make
progress on some kind of task.
So, you can train them in
environments where they take longer and
longer, and then put them in a
completely new environment, and they may
not have generalized the
reasoning patterns that will allow them to
perform well in that environment, but
at least they have generalized the ability
to continue with that task for
longer, which correlates with
success.  For example, there is an article
called Edge Bench that showed that the
rate at which models can
run for longer
doubles every 3 months.  And that is
clear evidence of generalization.  And I
think the final way of thinking about it is
like, uh, in pre-workout there's
this idea of ​​how many.  So, you have
this
very smooth pre-workout loss curve.  And when
you really look at what's
happening in the model, how the model
is learning all these
very discrete tasks, there are all these
emerging points.  There's like a kind of
phase transition.  As if it didn't have
induction heads before, now it has
induction heads and there are like
tens of thousands, millions,
probably like hundreds of millions
of these things.  And you average them all
together and you get this
very smooth loss curve.  I think that to some
extent something similar is
happening with RL.  As if there were
this very slow outer loop as
Bear mentioned, you know, we'll train
a model and then apply it to
machine learning and then, in the
next iteration of the
training model, we'll dump a bunch of
these synthetic reasoning traces
into the mid-
training data.  It's as if we're
hitting all these quants for
all these different tasks, and at the
individual task level, it may
look like a phase transition, and as if you
suddenly go from a
0.5% pass rate to a
90% pass rate on a
particular finance or Excel task, but
if you average all these
things and add up the
horizon generalization, in a way you would go up,
we have qualitatively
better models.
Yes. I mean, I think a lot of
this is good; it's like RL
generalizes a bit, like you
suddenly have something like a
transfer between math and
code or puzzles and math and
that kind of thing.  Furthermore, the
quantity, the sheer number of environments that I
believe people are targeting,
is much, much greater.  For example,
before, when you tried to do some
task that you do in your daily life, like
two years ago, the labs did
n't really care.  They hadn't
trained a model for it, and now it
's much broader.  They have many
environments that are geared towards this
specific thing.
At the beginning of the conversation,
we talked about the RL in the context of
causing this entropy collapse or,
simply, concentrating the probability
on solutions that the base model has already
made and causing
relatively dispersed updates in policy
.  But when I think about it, I think there's
another story about RL
that goes back to Atari games, and
then AlphaGo introduces move 37
, the super-creative move that, because it was
never initialized with human data,
can think in ways that
humans don't even think about and come up with
extremely creative solutions.
Yes, do you have any idea when
or if we should
expect RL in LLMs to lead
to things like the 37 movement,
just extreme creativity,
even beyond
human creativity because it's like there's a
de novo initialization of
intelligence?    I mean
, there are a couple of things here
.  Firstly, I think AlphaGo
is using MCTS, which obviously
explores more and things like that than the
usual policy gradients.
But I also think that, in a
way, RL doesn't necessarily reduce
creativity.  And, well, even if we look at it
, I think there's always something
qualitative, but if we look at the
OpenAI Hugging Face incident, these
models were generating several
zero days at once to get out of the
constrained environment.  And this is clearly a level
of creativity of the 37 movement, I think we
get it from the
general generalization properties of LLMs.    I do
n't think that
reinforcement learning is
completely destroying its level of
entropy.
Yes.
Especially in the long term.
Yes, that is, something that people
call creativity is simply
solving difficult problems.  So
movement 37 is obviously an
example of that, or writing some kind
of poem that satisfies a lot of
different restrictions.  So that's
something AI is going to be
extremely good at if it's trained
for it.  Then there is another way in
which the models, the diversity of their
results is much lower after
machine learning, and they develop
these tics.  And, although it may seem that the
models are good at writing, when
you do some kind of
distribution analysis, you discover that they reuse
certain themes all the time and use the
same character names all the
time.  So, it's not really
like you're getting the same
kind of diversity as when you get
human authors, but you are
getting a really good style.
So I think that kind of
diversity has definitely been
greatly reduced by real learning.  And
, in fact, now, as we were talking about
distillation before, that's something like
, yes, one thing that's
happening is that a lot of people are
distilling, uh, mainly from
Claude, that all the open weight models
write the same way as
Claude and use the same things, they have the
same tics.  So I find it a little
worrying that we're experiencing this
kind of emerging monoculture.
Yes. Again, I don't think this is
fundamental to actual learning
as a method, however.  And the
same goes for distillation; even with
distillation, as if you
were only training with the data, it's
as if yours isn't very broad.
That doesn't mean the
training method itself is incorrect in
any way.  It's like a
data problem, and I think many cases, like
the RL entropy collapse, are
basically due to the exploitation of
fairly simple checkers when you do
n't have a great diversity of
environments.  Because, for example, the
writing, I think presumably is
graded by some judge and the judge has a
specific text and the model is
learning to reward the judge and that's why it
collapses.  But this is really a
problem with the judge.  It's not a problem
with the RL in general.
Mhm.  Very good.
Super-fast predictions about the future.  So
, I want timelines on the
following questions.  When will
we have models that you can use?  This is what would
happen if you wanted to use them.
Basically, you hire them as
remote workers for all kinds of
office work.  Not only
coding, but also
video editing, law, paralegal,
etc.  It's like a real remote worker
with full computer use, with
literally a month of uninterrupted learning and
operation, and
execution of complex projects that
require interacting with other
people, etc., etc.  Everything a
human worker could do in a
month.
If you are instructed to use a browser or
whatever instead, the company
configures the information to be
accessible programmatically,
maybe in a couple of years;  But if it's not
browser-based, you can send
Slack messages, you can do all
these things.  I'd probably say
about a year.
Okay.
Yes, I mean, maybe for the
whole general, maybe 3 years,
but I think, as Charles says,
we'll end up with a lot of people making
their organizations more
AI-friendly.  And that's about
80-90% of the way there
.
So, the difference between 1
year and 3 years is that,
literally,
I think there will be a long tail of
miscellaneous tasks that any
human can perform and that will
take models quite a while to be able to
execute effectively.
Yes, they're offering everything from
computer skills to
basic cognitive abilities.  I mean, I think
this boils down to questions
like how quickly we can figure out
this kind of online learning and whether we can get
80-90% of the way there with
compacting and writing
files ourselves, etc., and that's my
big uncertainty.  I really don't know
.
And another example of something I
probably wouldn't be good at is if
I had to yell at someone to
get something at work or have to
pressure a person to
finish doing something.  The model isn't going
to do that.  He's just going to be
too nice.
Yes.
I would say there is a wide variation
in the quality of
human remote workers.  So, if
you try to hire someone from Upwork
to do a
software engineering project, there's going to be
a lot of variation.  It's often
quite difficult to get them to do
a good job or to pay attention
to all the feedback you receive.  And
I suppose in some cases it will be worse
;  The previous version of AI was worse
than what you can get now from the
existing AI.  So I think it could
end up being a bit complicated,
because maybe to some extent we already
have this, for example, for some
, it's not very high quality work,
but then it's obvious that we're not
... Yes, we're not matching the
human level in certain forms of
higher quality work.  Well, basically
I agree with Charlie and Barron
that maybe, yes, we will have
some version of this in a year or
so, okay, and it will be able to...uh,
maybe we'll have that form factor...
uh, and uh, it will be able to do some things
very well, some not so well, and yes,
things will improve from there.
As if we were constantly changing our
objective based on the very
long tail.  I feel like you used this
example before doing your taxes or
something.  This year, I literally
told Codex to go get everything I
needed to do and send it to the
accountant.  And there was a huge list of
things I had to check with
computers and download some things.
And I don't know, it was fine.  It was perfect.  I don't know
.  Many of these things you can already
do.
Yes. Okay.  It gives you a total
productivity increase of 10 times.  Basically
, if it now takes you a year to make a
big breakthrough, you'll make a big breakthrough every
month.    I
think I would refuse to give you a scale
for this.  We may have already
overcome that in some types of
work.  Let's say you're just trying to
prove that you're capable of doing
certain types of math.
So,
for you, as
AI researchers trying to advance the
state of AI research,
how much have AI researchers accelerated or improved
?
Between 5 and 10 years?
Really?  Yes, that's a long way off.
But does it last longer than the
general remote worker role?
Yes. Interesting.    I
think I'm probably realizing that you
probably have
very different definitions of a
general remote worker.  He could have been
a little more specific.
Yes, that's true, because it's clear
that an artificial intelligence researcher
can work
remotely.  And then,
yes, no.  I imagine something like a
normal office job over
a period of one month.
Yes.
I think it stops a little longer than
a month.
A highly competent office worker
, but not necessarily a
super-creative one.  researcher.
I'd say about 2 years.
2 years?
Yes.
10x, okay.  And you, Ben?
I can see it a little, actually.  Because
basically, right now, it's
definitely more than ten times
better when it comes to programming
.  And if I could do it with even one
or two experimental feedback loops
, that would be huge.
So, a 10x increase in
AI researchers in 2 years?  If you
connect it to a very naive model of
AI progress and how much of it comes from
AI researchers, you'll see that their
productivity increases 10x.  Yes, you have
a radically accelerated rate of
AI progress starting from 2 years.
Yes, I mean, I think this will
mean that AI progress will
not be hampered by the
ability of AI researchers
to conduct small experiments.    It will be
hindered by other things.
Of course, but it just happens
10 times faster.
Of course, yes.
Which is a great deal.  And that
also helps the next thing that
gives you 100 times greater speed
happen sooner, etc.
Yes, I'm happy to continue with that for a while longer
.  So
what's the crux of the matter?
My ability to absorb information
and make the optimal Bayesian decision
in the following experiment
makes sense.
Yes, I mean, I suppose you
can delegate some of this to AI.
So, AI is getting
decent at deciding, you know, run
this experiment, get this
result, run the next
experiment.  And then, if you can run
two or three experiments in a row without
failing, then that's a really
big upgrade.
And well, last question.  An AI that
surpasses the best human experts
in all fields could do a
job that can be done on a
computer.  Not just
AI research, but all cognitive work.  And not
just in the short term, but
literally, if it takes like 3 years or
so, AI will still be able to do it
better than humans.
Well, this is basically like this.
Okay.
I would say about 3 or 4 years.
What the hell?  I mean, that doesn't
seem wrong, but
I would say that artificial intelligence
is obviously getting a lot more
attention now.  It's one of the
most difficult things, but a
lot of energy is being invested in it, and it's not
one of the most
difficult things for AI either, because it involves a
lot of code and math, something
that models are very good at.
Perhaps for things involving 3D,
spatial and physical things, I think that will
take a little longer.
Well, especially if it's not
something like mechanical engineering and
that, and it's not getting the most
attention right now, it might
take a little longer.
But it also does not include fields where there is
relatively little data due to the
nature of the field and it has to
learn that data on the fly.
For example, he has to become
superhuman, like being an engineer at TSMC
or something like that.
Oh yeah, then you'd have to assume
that, like in onboarding, yeah,
you can give AI the same
onboarding material and uh, but then there's
something that needs to be worked out about, like,
some kind of long-
term learning or yeah.
At 7.5 to 10. So basically,
yes, you think automating
AI research is like
full AGI or something.
Yes, I think so.  Um, yes.  I think there are
many things in the world that,
even if you have some kind of
external memory system to the model and
even if, for example, the length
of the context grows a little, there are
fundamental things like, even if you could
research the information or write
notes yourself, you would need more than
a minute to take the
context field today.  Yes.
Yes, I mean, I agree with
the 5-year timeframe, at least as far as
the things
the labs are focusing on are concerned.  But I think
there will be a long list of things
that, in theory, it could go out and
learn about, but nobody has bothered to
do it and the computer hasn't been
allocated for that.  So it could take
longer for, literally, all
the human experts.
Yes. That's true, but my latest AI
also includes the ability to
learn as quickly as a human in
a new domain.    I mean
, I don't think that's
necessarily necessary, really,
because AI will have much more
experience than any human.
Correct.  Actually, it's a good
debate.  I think this is a great
format for different experts to
disagree, debate, and discuss things
together.  It was very productive.
Brilliant.
Thank you for inviting us.
You.
Of course.  Thank you for inviting us.